Mss.Rec.76 Mss.Rec.76
American Philosophical Society
Diegueño texts
1963-1964
Mss.Rec.76
American Philosophical Society
3.0 Reel(s)
Field recordings made with Kumiai (Diegueño) speakers from numerous communities in San Diego County, California, and Sonora, Mexico. Primarily consists of traditional stories, including Coyote stories. Also includes word lists, conversations, description of the preparation of acorns for food, identification of museum artifacts, and an extended account of the Mission Indian Federation.
3 sound tape reels (6 hr., 34 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 track, mono; 7 in.
Hinton, Leanne
Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Margaret Langdon in 1970. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Acorns as food; Coyote (Legendary character)--Legends; Foxes--Folklore; Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kamia Indians--Social life and customs; Kamia Indians--Songs and music; Kumiai language; Mission Indian Federation; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Identification of Diegueno artifacts at Museum of Man, 1963; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:50; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Lopez, Ortiz; Robertson, Rosalie
    Scope and Contents note
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Mission Valley dialect. The program contains some print-through of audio elsewhere on the tape.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Kamia Indians--Material culture; San Diego (Calif.)
  - Word list, 1963-04-28; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:00; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Robertson, Rosalie
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Campo dialect. The program contains some print-through of audio elsewhere on the tape.
    Campo Indian Reservation (Calif.); Kumiai language
  - How God made relatives, 1963; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:59; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Largo, Teneslado
    Campo Indian Reservation (Calif.); Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language
  - Women crying in ritual fashion at wake, 1963-05-04; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:07; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Largo, Teneslado
    Campo Indian Reservation (Calif.); Kamia Indians--Social life and customs
  - General talk including star lore, circa 1963; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:57:04; Kwaha, Fernando; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Robertson, Rosalie
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Ha'a dialect.
    Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; Sonora (Mexico: State); Stars--Folklore
  - Three songs, with discussion, circa 1963; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:46; Hinton, Leanne; Juan; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the La Huerta dialect.
    Kamia Indians--Songs and music; Kumiai language; La Huerta (Sonora, Mexico)
  - Coyote baptizes the chickens, circa 1963; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:20; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Murillo, Alejandrina
    Coyote (Legendary character)--Legends; Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; La Huerta (Sonora, Mexico)
  - Stinkbug and Coyote (Spanish), circa 1963; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:00; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Machado, Anjelina
  - Stinkbug and Coyote (Kumiai), circa 1963; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:36; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Murillo, Alejandrina
  - The singing burro (Kumiai), circa 1963; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:54; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Machado, Anjelina
    Donkeys--Folklore; Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; La Huerta (Sonora, Mexico)
  - The singing burro (Spanish), circa 1963; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:43; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Machado, Anjelina
  - Conversation between Maria Aldama and Matias' wife, circa 1963; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:05; Aldama, Maria; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speakers are identified as speakers of the La Huerta dialect.
    Kumiai language; La Huerta (Sonora, Mexico)
  - Preparation of acorns, circa 1963; 02-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:41; Aldama, Maria; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    Acorns as food; Kamia Indians--Food; Kumiai language; La Huerta (Sonora, Mexico)
  - Fox and Coyote, circa 1963; 02-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:52; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Murillo, Alejandrina
    Coyote (Legendary character)--Legends; Foxes--Folklore; Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; La Huerta (Sonora, Mexico)
  - Fox and the moon, circa 1963; 02-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:41; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Machado, Anjelina
    Foxes--Folklore; Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; La Huerta (Sonora, Mexico)
  - Mountain lion and Coyote, circa 1963; 02-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:38; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Machado, Anjelina
    Coyote (Legendary character)--Legends; Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; La Huerta (Sonora, Mexico); Puma--Folklore
  - The Two Sisters who went away, circa 1963; 02-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:47; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Robertson, Rosalie
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Campo dialect.
    Campo Indian Reservation (Calif.); Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; Sisters--Folklore
  - First woman [2 of 2], circa 1963; 02-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:33; La Chappa, Mary Leon; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Cuyapaipe-Jamul dialect.
    Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - General conversation and 'bad songs', circa 1963; 02-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:19; La Chappa, Mary Leon; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Robertson, Rosalie
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Campo dialect. The program contains print-through of audio elsewhere on the tape.
    Kamia Indians--Social life and customs; Kamia Indians--Songs and music; Kumiai language; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - The Fish People, circa 1963; 02-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:31; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Thing, Isabel
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Jamul dialect. The program contains print-through of audio elsewhere on the tape.
  - First woman [1 of 2], circa 1963; 02-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:44; La Chappa, Mary Leon; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Cuyapaipe-Jamul dialect. The program contains print-through of audio elsewhere on the tape.
  - Reminiscences of childhood, circa 1964; 02-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:21; Barrett, Florence; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Baron Long dialect.
    Childhood; Kumiai language; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - Testing of audio equipment, circa 1964; 02-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:41; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    San Diego County (Calif.)
  - Unidentified text, circa 1964; 02-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:53; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    Kumiai language; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - The Lord's Prayer (incomplete), circa 1964; 02-20; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:57; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Ponchetti, Steve
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Mesa Grande dialect.
    Kumiai language; Lord's Prayer; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - The Lord's Prayer, circa 1964; 02-21; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:56; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Ponchetti, Steve
  - The Serenity Prayer, circa 1964; 02-22; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:37; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005; Ponchetti, Steve
    Kumiai language; San Diego County (Calif.); Serenity prayer
  - The Story of Chaup, circa 1964; 02-23; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:01; Hutcheson, Christina; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
  - Jonny Bear, circa 1964; 02-24; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:59; Couro, Ted; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Mesa Grande dialect. Volume drops out between 12:24 and 13:13.
  - Conversation between Ted Couro and Christina Hutcheson, 1964-03-21; 02-25; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:42; Couro, Ted; Hutcheson, Christina; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speakers are identified as speakers of the Mesa Grande dialect.
    Escondido (Calif.); Kumiai language
  - How to prepare acorn, circa 1964; 02-26; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:01; Hutcheson, Christina; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    Acorns as food; Kamia Indians--Food; Kumiai language; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - Coyote and Rabbit; Coyote and Mountain Lion, circa 1964; 02-27; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:42; La Chappa, Maria Paipa; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Inyaja dialect.
    Coyote (Legendary character)--Legends; Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; Puma--Folklore; Rabbits--Folklore; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - Story of Eagle Peak, circa 1964; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:07; Alto, Rebecca; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Santa Ysabel dialect.
    Kamia Indians--Folklore; Kumiai language; Mountains--Folklore; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - Word list, circa 1964; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:06; Hutcheson, Christina; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
  - General talk about the Mission Indian Federation, circa 1964; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:16; Ames, Ramon; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005
    The speaker is identified as a speaker of the Barona dialect.
    Indians of North America--California; Kumiai language; Mission Indian Federation; San Diego County (Calif.)
  - General talk about the Mission Indian Federation continued, circa 1964; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:37:44; Ames, Ramon; Langdon, Margaret, 1926-2005